"Does Aluminum Cause Alzheimer's Disease?"
The so-called
"aluminum hypothesis"
for the cause
of Alzheimer's disease
dates back to 1965,
when the inadvertent
injection of aluminum
into the brains of rabbits
caused neurological symptoms
along with what initially
looked like Alzheimer's disease
tangles in the brain.
Then, in the 1970s,
it was first reported
that the aluminum content
of Alzheimer's brains
was higher than that
of control brains on autopsy.
Following that, there was
a rash of fatal dementia cases
attributed to dialysis fluids
contaminated with aluminum.
This trio of findings
led researchers
to suggest that aluminum,
the third most
abundant element on Earth
(after oxygen and silicon),
may play a role
in the development
of Alzheimer's disease.
The first crack in the theory
was the realization that,
upon closer inspection,
the tangle-like changes
in rabbit brains
were not much like those
found in human
Alzheimer's disease after all.
The changes in aluminum-induced
dialysis encephalopathy
were also dissimilar.
Aluminum could certainly
be toxic to the brain,
but not necessarily in a way
that had anything to do
with Alzheimer's disease.
And, subsequent autopsy studies
of Alzheimer's victims
did not consistently find
higher aluminum levels,
and even if they did,
elevations in brain aluminum
could be a consequence
rather than a cause
(reflecting
Alzheimer's disease damage
to the blood brain barrier).
The aluminum hypothesis
came under heavy fire
in the scientific community.
Only later did we learn
that the most vocal critics
were secretly-paid
aluminum industry hacks.
In hindsight,
that was probably unnecessary,
as the tide of evidence
eventually turned against
the role of aluminum.
What convinced me
was a meta-analysis
that failed to find a connection
between regular antacid use
and Alzheimer's.
Processed foods
contain a variety
of aluminum-containing
additives,
such as anti-caking agents
in pancake mix,
melting agents
in American cheese,
meat binders, gravy thickeners,
rising agents
in some baking powders,
and dye binders in candy.
However,
over-the-counter antacids
are probably
the most important source
for human aluminum exposure
in terms of dose.
In terms of the safety
of dietary aluminum,
the tolerable weekly intake
is 1 mg per healthy kilogram
of body weight.
So, if you weigh
about 150 pounds (67.5 kg),
you shouldn't get more than,
like, 10 milligrams a day.
One day of Maalox
can give you
38 hundred milligrams,
nearly 400 times
the daily safety limit,
and nowhere on the label
does it say
not to take
with acidic beverages,
such as fruit juice.
Washing an antacid down
with orange juice
can increase
aluminum absorption eight-fold.
The total aluminum intake
in drinking water
and processed foods
in most countries may only
be a few milligrams a day.
But, some antacids can increase
daily aluminum consumption
by up to several grams,
a thousand-fold higher.
And so, if antacid use
isn't related
to Alzheimer's risk,
then ingested aluminum
is unlikely to be a cause.
Now, as I explored
in my video on cooking with it,
just because aluminum
doesn't cause Alzheimer's
doesn't mean aluminum intake
is necessarily benign.
Those who cook with aluminum
and store acidic foods,
like yogurt and tomato,
in aluminum cookware
suffer significantly more
DNA damage,
leading some regulators
to recommend consumers
avoid the use
of aluminum pots or dishes
for acidic or salted foodstuffs.
In my video on antiperspirants
and breast cancer,
I note how the FDA
and European safety authorities
specifically advise against
using aluminum antiperspirants
on damaged skin,
which may even include
avoiding them after shaving.
As a "metalloestrogen,"
aluminum absorption may explain
why breast cancer may occur
as much as twenty years earlier
in women using antiperspirant
and shaving their armpits
more than three times a week.
You can also avoid
high dietary sources
by choosing non-aluminum
baking powder for baking
and avoiding
processed cheese.
Aluminum salts can give cheese
"desirable slicing properties,"
but that means a single
grilled cheese sandwich
can end up exceeding
the World Health Organization's
provisional tolerable
daily intake of aluminum
by as much as 400 percent.